Vlad Merticariu

Jacobs University, Bremen, Germany
Large-Scale Scientific Information Systems Research Group

Summary

Vlad is a computer scientist with a vast expertise in distributed systems, databases, geospatial standards and web service standards compliance. He is a contributor to the rasdaman array database engine, as well as OGC WCS standards ecosystem. Vlad's research interest falls under the category of parallel query processing: a network of machines collaborate for answering a single array database query, by dividing it into independent subqueries sent to different servers.

Education

Currently he is completing his PhD entitled “Data Fragmentation and Replication in Distributed Array Databases” at Jacobs University Bremen, in which he focuses on finding strategies for dynamically partitioning and replicating large amounts of incoming data, with the purpose of maximizing parallelism of outgoing processing operations.

Key publications

On the Efficient Evaluation of the Array Joins. Peter Baumann, Vlad Merticariu. IEEE Big Data, Santa Clara, USA, 2015.

Grooming Big Data from Afar. Peter Baumann, Alex Mircea Dumitru, Vlad Merticariu. ACM SigSpatial, Seattle, USA, 2015.

Exploring Cloud Opportunities from an Array Database Perspective. Peter Baumann , Alex Mircea Dumitru, Vlad Merticariu. DANAC, SIGMOD, Snowbird, USA, 2014.

The array database that is not a database: file based array query answering in rasdaman. Peter Baumann, Alex Mircea Dumitru, Vlad Merticariu. SSTD, Munich, USA, 2013.

Breaking the big data barrier by enhancing on-board sensor flexibility. Peter Baumann, Alex Mircea Dumitru, Vlad Merticariu, D. Misev. ACM BigSpatial, Orlando, USA, 2013

Projects

Earthserver project: lead developer for the data partitioning and replication features of rasdaman in distributed environments, developer for the OGC web services offered by rasdaman.

Publicamundi project: co-manager of the project.

Modelling and mapping the Natural Forest Distribution of Italy and predicting changes for the year 2080 under IPCC SRES A2a scenario

Objective

The object of this work is to simulate potential changes of Italian natural forest distribution under climate change scenarios. Download full presentation.

Introduction

In the period between 1950 and 2000, natural disturbance has caused several million cubic meters of forest damage each year (Schelhaas et al. 2003). An increase of forest damage can be foreseen directly and indirectly due to climate change projections (McCarthy et al. 2001). In the latest decades not only have damaged areas been reforested, but a trend of afforestation of agricultural land has been observed with a general increase in forested land (Kuusela 1996). European forest landscapes are changing shape and content. Next century afforestation and reforestation will be a crucial decision and policy-making topic in the context of landscape management towards European sustainability. Our study is linked to conservation policy making, approaching theoretical distributional modelling, ecological theory and applied landscape management. This is achieved by combining fine resolution predictors with homogeneous and dense field data by means of robust modelling techniques.
Within this applied spatial ecoogical modeling theme, we modelled actual and future Natural forest categories in Italy and estimated the shifts in vegetation in the period 2000–2080 under the IPCC SRES A2a scenario. The actual and future distribution of the 10 most dominant European Forest Categories (EEA, 2006) are simulated using the Random Forest classifier. Random Forest is an ensemble of model machine-learning techniques and relates to the natural forest formations in Italy and environmental predictor surface maps.
Environmental predictor variables have a resolution of 1km^2 pixel and include soil factors (European Soil Database), bioclimatic factors (Worldclim database, Hijmans et al. 2005) and topographic factors (SRTM digital elevation model). See Input Data section.
According to the future climatic simulation we expect Mediterranean vegetation to gain suitability areas and temperate forest to decrease their extent. In mountainous areas vegetation belts are expected to shift towards upper altitude levels.

Method

In our approach we model the current distribution of the natural forest in Italy according to environmental variables. In order to do so we are going to construct an input response / predictor table relating the distribution of the Natural forest formations in Italy to climatic, soil and geomorphologic factors. Successively we use the input response / predictor table and the machine-learning ensemble classifier Random Forest (Breiman, 2001) to create a forest type / environmental factors predictive model.
Once the model is trained for the current climate we are going project vegetation shift under future climate conditions.

Input Data

As input data we use the following datasets:

Map of the Natural Vegetation of Europe (Bohn et al. 2000) reclassified in forest categories according to the European Forest Types (EEA 2006) classification scheme.

Climatic data: twenty years averaged monthly minimum, maximum and accumulated precipitation from the http://www.worldclim.org datasets (Hijmans et al., 2005) and derived bioclimatic factors as described in Casalegno et al. 2010 see predictor_table

Future climate projections derived from the http://worldclim.org datraset. We use the IPCC Special Report on Emission Scenario A2a storyline (IPCC, 2001) future climate projection simulated by an averaged Genaral Circulation Model GCM. Original averaged GCM are HADCM3 (Hadley Centre Coupled Model version 3) (Collins et al., 2001), CCCMA (Canadian Centre for Climate Modelling and Analysis) (Kim et al., 2003), CSIRO (Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation) (Gordon and O’Farrell, 1997).

Geo-morphological factors derived from the SRTM digital elevation model (Farr et al., 2007) minimum, maximum, mean altitudes, altitude standard deviation, slope and dominant orientation (north, south, east, west).

Soil variables selected from the European Soil Database (King et al., 1995; Heineke et al., 1998): soil parent material (eight classes) and FAO soil type classification (25 classes).

Computational Implementation

You can reproduce the case study and learn how to use open source tools following the command lines of each script step by step. Scripts are available online in a wiki format. This format may cause trouble when copying and pasting command syntax into the terminal. Be careful! Scripts are also available to download online and are stored on your local virtual machine. (see links below). If you choose to use the sripts we recommend using a text editor and to add your comments.

You have the choice of reproducing the case study by downloading scripts online or to open on your local machine. The modeling and mapping procedure includes the following steps and relative scripts:

Generate a response predictor input table using a bash shell / grass script: Download the shell script here or follow the shell script in wiki format

Modeling the current distribution of the Natural Forest Vegetation of Italy: Download the .R script here or follow the R script in wiki format

Mapping the current Natural Forest Vegetation in Italy: Download the R script here or follow the R script in wiki format

Generate future climate prediction surface map for the year 2080 and the IPCC A2a ENS model: Download the bash shell / grass script here or follow the shell script in wiki format

Mapping the future projections of the Natural Forest Vegetation in Italy: Download the R script here or follow the R script in wiki format

Bibliography

Bohn U., Gollub G., Hettwer C. 2000. Map of the Natural Vegetation of Europe. Bonn: Federal Agency for Nature Conservation.

Breiman, L., 2001. Random forests. Machine Learning 45 (1), 5–32.

Collins, M., Tett, S., Cooper, C., 2001. The internal climate variability of hadcm3, a version of the hadley centre coupled model without flux adjustments. Climate Dynamics 17, 61–68.

EEA 2006. European Forest Types: Categories and types for sustainable forest management reporting and policy. European Environmental Agency Technical report no 9/2006. Copenhagen. ISSN 175-2237.

Farr, T. G., Rosen, P., Caro, E., Crippen, R., Duren, R., Hensley, S., Kobrick, M., Paller, M., Rodriguez, E., Roth, L., Seal, D., Shaffer, S., Shimada, J., Umland, J., Werner, M., Oskin, M., Burbank, D., Alsdorf, D., 2007. The shuttle radar topography mission. Rev. Geophys 45.

Gordon, H., O’Farrell, S., 1997. Transient climate change in the csiro coupled model with dynamic sea ice. Monthly Waether Review 125(5), 875907.

Heineke, H., Eckelmann, W., Thomasson, A., Jones, R., Montanarella, L., Buckley, B., 1998. Land Information Systems Developments for planning the sustainable use of land resources. Research Report. European Soil Boureau, Luxembourg.

Hijmans, R. J., S.E. Cameron, J.L. Parra, Jones, P. G., and Jarvis, A., 2005: Very high resolution interpolated

   climate surfaces for global land areas. International Journal of Climatology, 25: 1965-1978

* IPCC, 2001. Climate Change 2001: The Scientific Basis. Contribution of Working Group I to the Third Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, cambridge university press Edition. Cambridge University Press,, Cambridge, United Kingdom.

Kim, S.-J., Flato, G., Boer, G., 2003. A coupled climate model simulation of the last glacial maximum, part 2: approach to equilibrium climate. Dynamics 20, 635–661.

King, D., Jones, R., Thomasson, A., 1995. European Land Information Systems for Agro-environmental Monitoring. Office for the Official Publications of the European Communities, Luxembourg.

Kuusela, K. 1996. Forest resources in Europe 1950-1990. Cambridge University Press.

McCarthy JJ, Canziani OF, et al. (eds) (2001) Climate Change 2001: Impacts, Adaptation, and Vulnerability. Contribution of Working Group II to the Third Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC). Cambridge University Press, Cambridge.

Shelhaas, M-J., Nabuurs, G-J., Schuck, A..2003. Natural disturbances in the European forests in the 19th and 20th centuries. Global Change Biology:, 1620–1633.

Command/filename completion

When you use the bash shell on Linux it will complete commands and file names for you if you type the 'TAB' key. The default behavior is: 1. You type in the start of the command or filename. 2. You hit TAB. 3. The shell will fill in as much as it can and beep. 4. Hit TAB again and it shows you all possible matches.

Example: Type: “tai” and pres tab

tai

Type: “ta” and pres tab 2 times

tai

Keyboard shortcuts

Ctrl + a Go to the beginning of the line you are currently typing on.
Ctrl + E Go to the end of the line you are currently typing on.
Ctrl + l Clears the Screen, similar to the clear command.
Ctrl + u Clears the line before the cursor position. If you are at the end of the line, clears the entire line.
Ctrl + h Same as backspace.
Ctrl + r Let’s you search through previously used commands.
Ctrl + c Kill whatever you are running.
Ctrl + d Exit the current shell.
Ctrl + z Puts whatever you are running into a suspended background process. fg restores it.
Ctrl + w Delete the word before the cursor.
Ctrl + k Clear the line after the cursor.
Ctrl + t Swap the last two characters before the cursor.
Esc + t Swap the last two words before the cursor.
Alt + f Move cursor forward one word on the current line.
Alt + b Move cursor backward one word on the current line.
Tab Auto-complete files and folder names.

The most important shortcuts Keyboard shortcuts are
Ctrl + a
Ctrl + c
Ctrl + e
Ctrl + k
Start to use it from the beginning and you will coding very fast!

Limited filling of the potential Pinus cembra range

Introduction

Pinus Cembra (Pinaceae L.) or Swiss Stone Pine is a localised and endemic tree species that occurs in the alpine timberline. We are going to calculate the realized / potential range size ratio (range filling R/P) for the alpine Pine Pinus cembra as a measure of how well this species fulfills its potential range Gaston 2003. We use the Pinus cembra habitat suitability modeling Casalegno et al., 2010 and the Pinus cembra distribution map euforgen database to estimate R/P ratio.

P is the total number of Pinus cembra suitable pixels within the study area.

R is the number of Pinus cembra suitable pixels within the Pinus cembra distribution maps pixels.

This will quantify the extent to which Pinus cembra fulfills its modelled suitability range in the Alps. We computed the realized / potential range size ratio (R/P) across the Alpine and Carpathian mountains area.

Start a new GRASS project and define a region of analysis

We open a terminal and go to the directory corresponding to our GRASS LOCATION.

cd ~/ost4sem/grassdb/europe

We copy the PERMANENT MAPSET and rename it PCEM. PCEM will be our new MAPSET and grass project where we store maps for calculating the R/P ratio.

rm -r PCEM
cp -r PERMANENT PCEM

We start grass in the newest PCEM mapset

grass -text  ~/ost4sem/grassdb/europe/PCEM

Look at the default g.region and redefine a study area including the Carpathian and Alpine mountain ranges. Set the new working region at 1km resolution and call it alpine:

g.region -d
g.region -p
g.region --o n=3070000 s=2270000 w=3900000 e=5660000 res=1000 save=alp_car
g.region -p

Pinus Cembra distribution map: data preparation

Import and reclass distribution map

Import the Euforgen Pinus cembra distribution map from the euforgen web page and convert it from a shape file to a raster file :

v.in.ogr dsn=~/ost4sem/exercise/rp_ratio/pcem_euforgen/Pinuscembra_LAEA.shp output=pcem_euforgen --overwrite

Convert the vector file to a raster file, look at the pixels values and reclass this map into a binary presence and absence of Pinus cembra distribution.

You can open Qgis within the grass section and continue to work with grass using the following command

qgis &

Once you have opened Qgis, load the pcem_euforgen@PCEM vector map and check which source of raster values you have to use for the conversion from vector to raster. You have the choice between: attr,cat,val,z,dir.

v.to.rast --o input=pcem_euforgen@PCEM output=pcem_euforgen use=cat
v.info pcem_euforgen
r.info pcem_euforgen

The raster we generate has values running from 1 to 14 but we need a presence-absence map so we have to reclassify the pcem_euforgen raster into 0 - 1 map values.

r.mapcalc pcem_euforgen = "if(pcem_euforgen > 0 , 1 ,0 )"

Pinus Cembra suitability map: data preparation

Import and resize suitability map

Import the random forest model of suitability for Pinus cembra

r.in.gdal -o -e input=~/ost4sem/exercise/rp_ratio/pcem_randomforest/gdwarp_PRESENT.tif output=pcem_potential --o

Visualise the actual suitability of Pinus cembra acccording to the Random Forest Model

d.mon start=x3
d.rast pcem_potential

Calculate the realised range of Pinus Cembra suitability

The Potential distribution map or suitability map pcem_potential has values equal to:

1 : No suitable or no potential

2 : Suitable or Potential

20: Sea

The distribution map pcem_euforgen has values equal to:

NoData: absence

1: presence

If we sum the two maps we will be able to generate a realized range map. This is done by selecting class 3 from the sum of the two maps. Class 3 represents suitable pixels within the presence of distribution.

r.mapcalculator amap=pcemeuforgen bmap=pcempotential formula=A+B outfile=pcemrealized –overwrite r.mapcalc pcemrealized = “if(pcem_realized == 3 , 1 ,0 )”

You visualize and save results for the Realized area in a text file with the following commands:

r.report -n map=pcem_realized units=k
r.report -n map=pcem_realized units=k > ~/ost4sem/exercise/rp_ratio/results/R_value.txt

The R (realised distribution range) is equal to 24,606 square Kilometres.

You visualize and save results for the Potential area in a text file with the following commands:

 r.report -n map=pcem_potential units=k 
 r.report -n map=pcem_potential units=k > ~/ost4sem/exercise/rp_ratio/results/P_value.txt

The P (potential distribution range) is equal to 32,538 square Kilometres.

The RP ratio ⇒ 24,606 / 32,538 % 100 = 75 %

Bibliography

Casalegno S., G. Amatulli, A. Camia, A. Nelson, A. Pekkarinen. 2010. Vulnerability of Pinus cembra L. in the Alps and the Carpathian mountains under present and future climates. Forest Ecology and Management 259: 70-761.

Gaston 2003. The Structure and Dynamics of Geographic Ranges. Series: OXFORD SERIES IN ECOLOGY AND EVOLUTION. Kevin J Gaston 266 pages, Oxford University Press. ISBN-10: 0198526407.

Introduction to R

The object of this document is to help you starting to use the R environment for statistical analysis and graphics.
You can read and follow the the text. Meanwhile you can copy the commands included into the frames part of this document, and paste them into an interactive R session.
Once you are familiar with the general functioning of R and of R's objects you can further advance in learning R with online manuals and guides. There is a great variety of documentation available at:

www.r-project.org.

http://www.statmethods.net/index.html

http://wiki.r-project.org/rwiki/doku.php

As well efficacious learning tools we would recommend that the user experiment with commands by, for example, trying different options to those stated. This experimentation is an important part of learning R using this synthetic document.

Starting R, getting help, stopping R

Start R

from a shell window type

R

In the bash terminal the following text will appear:

R version 2.10.0 (2009-10-26)
Copyright (C) 2009 The R Foundation for Statistical Computing
ISBN 3-900051-07-0
R is free software and comes with ABSOLUTELY NO WARRANTY.
You are welcome to redistribute it under certain conditions.
Type 'license()' or 'licence()' for distribution details.
Natural language support but running in an English locale\\
R is a collaborative project with many contributors.
Type 'contributors()' for more information and
'citation()' on how to cite R or R packages in publications.
Type 'demo()' for some demos, 'help()' for on-line help, or
'help.start()' for an HTML browser interface to help.
Type 'q()' to quit R.

the > sign and the following blinking cursor is advising you are in the R environment. If you like, enter in administrative mode type sudo R and you will be able to install packages

stefano@stefano-linux:~\$ sudo R

Getting help

R provides help with function and commands. On-line help gives useful information as well. Getting used to R help is a key to successful statistical modelling. The online help can be accessed in HTML format by typing:

  help.start()

A keyword search is possible using the Search Engine and Keywords link. You can also use the help() or ? functions. For example, if we want to know how to use the matrix() function, the following two commands are equivalents:

  help(matrix)
  ? matrix

Once you are in the help section, you can use “enter” to scroll down the menu and q to go back at the R prompt.

The str(object.name) command is used to display the internal structure of an R object
The summary(object.name) command gives a summary of a a object, usually a statistical summary but it is generic meaning it has different operations for different classes of a

dir() show files in the current directory
ls.str() str() for each variable in the search path
getwd() is asking for the current working directory

Stop R

  q()

When you quit, R will ask you if you want to save the workspace (that is, all of the variables you have defined in this session); say “no” in order to avoid clutter.

Should an R command seem to be stuck or take longer than you’re willing to wait, type Control-C.

Calling linux shell scripting commands

system(“…”) is used to call any linux scripting commands within the R environment

 system("pwd")
 # is equal to write 
 getwd()

Inputs and outputs

Once you have opened an R session and eventually loaded the library you need, you can start exploring your data

Loading data

load(file.name) function, loads R type datasets written with the save function load(file.name)

Saving data

save(object.name.1, object.name.2, … ) function save the specified object in XDR platform independent binary format

Reading tables

read.table(“filename”) Reads a file in table format and creates a data frame from it, with cases corresponding to lines and variables to fields within the file. The default separator sep=“” is any whitespace. You might need sep=“,” or “;” and so on. Use header=TRUE to read the first line as a header of column names. The as.is=TRUE specification is used to prevent character vectors from being converted to factors. The comment.char=““ specification is used to prevent ”#” from being interpreted as a comment and use skip=n to skip n lines before reading data;
For more datails

  ? read.table
 
  landuse04=read.csv("~/ost4sem/exercise/basic_adv_r/inputs/2004_landuse.csv", header=TRUE, sep=",", dec=".", na.string=":")

read.csv(“filename”) is set to read comma separated files. read.csv(file.name, header = TRUE, sep = “,”, quote=“\”“, dec=”.“, fill =TRUE, comment.char=”“, …)

read.delim(“filename”) is set for reading tab-delimited files

read.fwf() reads a table of fixed width formatted data into a ’data.frame’; widths is an integer vector, giving the widths of the fixed-width fields

Show variables and data in your workspace

The list function ls() outputs a list of existing R objects

  ls()

the structure function str(object.name) informs you of the structure of a specific object the summary function summary(object.name) informs you of basic statistics of a specific object

Save and remove data or R objects

save(file, …) saves the specified objects (…) in the XDR platform-independent binary format

  save(landuse04, file="~/ost4sem/exercise/basic_adv_r/outputs/landuse2004")

save.image(file) saves all objects

  save(file="~/ost4sem/exercise/basic_adv_r/outputs/landuse2004_and_more")

rm(file, …) removes the object you created or data you uploaded

  rm(landuse04)

No objects are present in memory now, use ls function to check it

  ls()
  character(0)

But since you saved the landuse2004 data you can reload it using the load() function and check its structrure using the str function

  load("~/ost4sem/exercise/basic_adv_r/outputs/landuse2004")
  str(landuse04)

as a result you will see the following information:

'data.frame':   72 obs. of  13 variables:                    
$ geographic.Unit                     : Factor w/ 72 levels "be10 Région de Bruxelles-Capitale/Brussels Hoofdstedelijk Gewest",..: 20 17 16 22 19 18 15 2 1 8 ...                                                                                                                                            
 $ landuse                             : logi  NA NA NA NA NA NA ...                                                                                   
 $ total.Total.area                    : num  NA NA NA NA NA ...                                                                                       
 $ agriarea.Utilized.agricultural.area : num  NA NA NA NA NA ...                                                                                       
 $ arabland.Arable.land                : num  NA NA NA NA NA ...                                                                                       
 $ forest.Wooded.area                  : num  NA NA NA NA NA ...
 $ garden.Private.gardens              : num  NA NA NA NA NA NA 0.2 0 0 0.1 ...
 $ grasland.Permanent.grassland        : num  NA NA NA NA NA ...
 $ greenfod.Green.fodder.on.arable.land: num  NA NA NA NA NA ...
 $ fallow.Fallow                       : num  NA NA NA NA NA NA 23.6 0 0 7.4 ...
 $ olivepl.Olive.plantations           : int  NA NA NA NA NA NA 0 0 0 0 ...
 $ permcrop.Permanent.crops            : num  NA NA NA NA NA NA 21.4 0 0 19.2 ...
 $ vineyard.Vineyards                  : num  NA NA NA NA NA NA 0 0 0 0 ...
>

Variables and calculations

R has an interactive calculations function. The command is executed and results are displayed.
R uses: +, -, /, and ^ for addition, subtraction, multiplication, division and exponentiation, respectively

2+2 

R will execute and display

[1] 4

the [1] at the beginning of the line is just R printing an index of element numbers. If you print a result that appears on multiple lines, R will put an index at the beginning of each line.

2*5
[1] 10

10/2
[1] 5

2^3
[1] 8

variable settings

you can simply create a variable by typing: variable name = function, constant or calculation.
Example:

x =3*2

The results of 3*2 is not displayed. In fact, the x variable value is stored in the memory without printing it. To display the x value you can use:

  print(x) 
  [1] 6

or

  x
  [1] 6

Most users apply a similar syntax using the '←' character string instead of the = character.

  x <- 3
  x
  [1] 3

Also remember that R is case sensitive, print(X) or X is different from x. For instance

  a <- 3
  a
  [1] 3
  A
  Error: object 'A' not found

Variable names in R must begin with a letter, followed by alphanumeric characters.

  3e = 2
  Error: unexpected input in "3e "

In long names you can use ”.“ or “_” as in

very.long.variable.name.X or verylongvariablenameY but you can’t use blank spaces in variable names. Avoid single letter names such us: c, l, q, t, C, D, F, I, and T, which are either built-in R functions or hard to tell apart.

  very.long.variable.name.X3 = 3
  very.long.variable.name.X3
  [1] 3

Interactive calculations

Once defined, you can use variables in interactive calculations :

  b = 2*2
  a = 2*3
  a*b
  [1] 24

And you can use variables in formulas :

  c = 60 /(a+b)
  c
 [1] 6

typing a;b you can display a and b variables at the same time:

 a;b
  [1] 6
  [1] 4

If you omit to close a parenthesis, R will display a + sign.

 c = 60 /(a+b
  +

In this case you can either close the parenthesis in the next line or type ctrl + c to go back to a new starting prompt.

Operators order

When using more complex formulas be aware of the importance of the order of operators. Parenthesis have priority over exponentiation, or powers, then comes multiplication and division, finally addition and subtraction. The following command:

  C = ((a + 2 * sqrt(b))/(a + 8 * sqrt(b)))/2
  C
  [1] 0.2272727

is different from:

  C = a + 2 * sqrt(b) / a + 8 * sqrt(b) / 2
  C
  [1] 14.66667

as well as

  100-40/2^4
  [1] 97.5

is different from:

  (100-40)/2^4 
  [1] 3.75

and

    -2^4
    [1] -16
 

is different from:

   (-2)^4
   [1] 16

Logical values

R can perform conditional tests and generate True or False values as results.
The logical operators are <, ⇐, >, >=, == for exact equality and != for inequality.

  x = 60
  x > 100
  [1] FALSE
 
  x == 70
  [1] FALSE
 
  x >   3
  [1] TRUE
 
  x = 100
  [1] TRUE

Logical values can be stored as variables:

x = 60
  logical.value =  x >  3
  logical.value
  [1] TRUE

In addition if c1 and c2 are logical expressions, then c1 & c2 is their intersection (“and”), c1 | c2 is their union (“or”), and ! !c1 is the negation of c1.

R objects

The entities R operates on are technically known as objects. Examples are vectors of numeric (real) or complex values, vectors of logical values and vectors of character strings. These are known as “atomic” structures since their components are all of the same type, or mode, namely numeric, complex, logical, character and raw. R also operates on objects called lists, which are of mode list. These are ordered sequences of objects which individually can be of any mode. Lists are known as “recursive” rather than atomic structures since their components can themselves be lists in their own right.

The other recursive structures are those of mode function and expression. Functions are the objects that form part of the R system along with similar user written functions, which we discuss in some detail later. Expressions as objects form an advanced part of R which will not be discussed in this guide, except indirectly when we discuss formulae used with modeling in R.

By the mode of an object we mean the basic type of its fundamental constituents. This is a special case of a “property” of an object. Another property of every object is its length. The functions mode(object) and length(object) can be used to find out the mode and length of any defined structure 10.

Further properties of an object are usually provided by attributes(object), (see 'Getting and setting attributes'). Because of this, mode and length are also called “intrinsic attributes” of an object. For example, if z is a complex vector of length 100, then in an expression mode(z) is the character string “complex” and length(z) is 100.

Vectors

Vectors are combinations of scalars in a string structure. Vectors must have all values of the same mode. Thus any given vector must be unambiguously either logical, numeric, complex, character or raw. (The only apparent exception to this rule is the special “value” listed as NA for quantities not available, but in fact there are several types of NA). Note that a vector can be empty and still have a mode. For example the empty character string vector is listed as character(0) and the empty numeric vector as numeric(0).

c(…) is the generic function to combine arguments with the default forming a vector; with RECURSIVE=TRUE descends through lists combining all elements into one vector.
To see details for the generic function c(…) and combine arguments forming a vector:

? c 

As an example we can create a simple vector of seven values typing:

  c(2,3,4,5,10,5,8)
  [1]  2  3  4  5 10  5  8

We can generate a sequence using the syntax :

  1:10
  [1]  1  2  3  4  5  6  7  8  9 10

seq()
We can generate the same sequence of 1:10 command using the seq() function. The syntax will be :

 seq(1,10)
  [1]  1  2  3  4  5  6  7  8  9 10

The seq() function “seq(from = number, to = number, by = number)” allow to create a vector starting from a value to another by a defined increment:

  seq(1,10, 0.25)
  [1]  1.00  1.25  1.50  1.75  2.00  2.25  2.50  2.75  3.00  3.25  3.50  3.75
  [13]  4.00  4.25  4.50  4.75  5.00  5.25  5.50  5.75  6.00  6.25  6.50  6.75
  [25]  7.00 7.25  7.50  7.75  8.00  8.25  8.50  8.75  9.00  9.25  9.50  9.75
  [37]  10.0
 
  seq(from = 1, to = 10, by =  0.25)
  [1]  1.00  1.25  1.50  1.75  2.00  2.25  2.50  2.75  3.00  3.25  3.50  3.75
  [13]  4.00  4.25  4.50  4.75  5.00  5.25  5.50  5.75  6.00  6.25  6.50  6.75
  [25]  7.00  7.25  7.50  7.75  8.00  8.25  8.50  8.75  9.00  9.25  9.50  9.75
  [37] 10.00

rep() The replicate function “rep(x,times)” enables you to replicate a vector several times in a more complex vector. Calculations can be included to form vectors as well and functions can be combined in the same command:

  one2tree = 1:3 
  rep(one2tree,10) 
 [1] 1 2 3 1 2 3 1 2 3 1 2 3 1 2 3 1 2 3 1 2 3 1 2 3 1 2 3 1 2 3
 
  c(10*0:10)
  [1]   0  10  20  30  40  50  60  70  80  90 100
 
  rep(c (5*40:1, 5*1:40, 5, 6,7,8, 3, 2001:2014), 2)
  [1]  200  195  190  185  180  175  170  165  160  155  150  145  140  135  130
  [16]  125  120  115  110  105  100   95   90   85   80   75   70   65   60   55
  [31]   50   45   40   35   30   25   20   15   10    5    5   10   15   20   25
  [46]   30   35   40   45   50   55   60   65   70   75   80   85   90   95  100
  [61]  105  110  115  120  125  130  135  140  145  150  155  160  165  170  175
  [76]  180  185  190  195  200    5    6    7    8    3 2001 2002 2003 2004 2005
  [91] 2006 2007 2008 2009 2010 2011 2012 2013 2014  200  195  190  185  180  175
  [106]  170  165  160  155  150  145  140  135  130  125  120  115  110  105  100
  [121]   95   90   85   80   75   70   65   60   55   50   45   40   35   30   25
  [136]   20   15   10    5    5   10   15   20   25   30   35   40   45   50   55
  [151]   60   65   70   75   80   85   90   95  100  105  110  115  120  125  130
  [166]  135  140  145  150  155  160  165  170  175  180  185  190  195  200    5
  [181]    6    7    8    3 2001 2002 2003 2004 2005 2006 2007 2008 2009 2010 2011
  [196] 2012 2013 2014
 
  rep(seq(1,3,0.5),3)
  [1] 1.0 1.5 2.0 2.5 3.0 1.0 1.5 2.0 2.5 3.0 1.0 1.5 2.0 2.5 3.0

Missing Values

In some cases the components of a vector or of an R object more in general, may not be completely known. When an element or value is “not available” or a “missing value” in the statistical sense, a place within a vector may be reserved for it by assigning it the special value NA.
Any operation on an NA becomes an NA.

The function is.na(x) gives a logical vector of the same size as x with value TRUE if and only if the corresponding element in x is NA.

   > z <- c(1:3,NA);  ind <- is.na(z)
   > ind
   [1] FALSE FALSE FALSE  TRUE

There is a second kind of “missing” values which are produced by numerical computation, the so-called Not a Number, NaN, values. Examples are 0/0 or Inf - Inf which both give NaN since the result cannot be defined sensibly.

  > Inf-Inf
  [1] NaN
  > 0/0
  [1] NaN

In summary, is.na(xx) is TRUE both for NA and NaN values. To differentiate these, is.nan(xx) is only TRUE for NaNs. Missing values are sometimes printed as <NA> when character vectors are printed without quotes.

  z <- c(1:3,NA)
  is.not.available <- is.na(z) 
  is.not.a.number <-is.nan(z)
 
  is.not.a.number
  [1] FALSE FALSE FALSE FALSE
  is.not.available 
  [1] FALSE FALSE FALSE  TRUE
 

Matrix

Matrices, or more generally arrays, are multi-dimensional generalizations of vectors. In fact, they are vectors that can be indexed by two or more indices and will be printed in a special way. See Arrays and matrices.

Factors provide compact ways to handle categorical data. See Factors.

Lists are a general form of vector in which the various elements need not be of the same type, and are often themselves vectors or lists. Lists provide a convenient way to return the results of a statistical computation. See Lists.

The matrix() function creates a matrix from the given set of values. We use the matrix(x, nrow=, ncol=) function to set the matrix cell values, the number of rows and the number of columns. We can use the colnames() and rownames() functions to set the column and row names of the matrix-like object.

  matrix(data = NA, nrow = 2, ncol = 3) 
  example.matrix = matrix(0,2,3)
  example.matrix
       [,1] [,2] [,3]
  [1,]    0    0    0
  [2,]    0    0    0
 
  example.matrix[1,]
  [1] 0 0 0
 
  example.matrix[,2]
  [1] 0 0
 
  example.matrix[1,] = 1:3
  example.matrix[2,] = c(5,10,4)
  example.matrix
       [,1] [,2] [,3]
  [1,]    1    2    3
  [2,]    5   10    4
 
 
  matrix.head = c("col a","col b","column c")
  matrix.side = c("first raw","second raw")
  str(matrix.side)
  chr [1:2] "first raw" "second raw"

When using ” “ we create and refer to a character type “chr” input

  numeric.vector = c(rep(c (5*10:1, 5, 6), 2))
  character.vector  = as.character(numeric.vector)
  str(character.vector)
  chr [1:24] "50" "45" "40" "35" "30" "25" "20" "15" "10" ...
 
 
  colnames(example.matrix) = matrix.head
  rownames(example.matrix) = matrix.side
  example.matrix
             col a col b column c
  first raw      1     2        3
  second raw     5    10        4
 
  str(example.matrix)
  num [1:2, 1:3] 1 5 2 10 3 4
   - attr(*, "dimnames")=List of 2
    ..$ : chr [1:2] "first raw" "second raw"
    ..$ : chr [1:3] "col a" "col b" "column c"

Array

An array can be considered a multiple subscripted collection of data entries, for example numeric. R allows simple facilities for creating and handling arrays, and in particular the special case of matrices.

As well as giving a vector structure a dim attribute, arrays can be constructed from vectors by the array function, which has the form
array(datavector, dimvector)

   Z <- array(1:24, c(3,4,2))
   Z
   , , 1
        [,1] [,2] [,3] [,4]
   [1,]    1    4    7   10
   [2,]    2    5    8   11
   [3,]    3    6    9   12
   , , 2
        [,1] [,2] [,3] [,4]
   [1,]   13   16   19   22
   [2,]   14   17   20   23
   [3,]   15   18   21   24

Data Frames

Data frames are matrix-like structures, in which the columns can be of different types. Think of data frames as data matrices with one row per observational unit but with (possibly) both numerical and categorical variables. Many experiments are best described by data frames: the treatments are categorical but the response is numeric.
As a result R dataframes are tightly coupled collections of variables which share many of the properties of matrices and of lists. Data frames are used as the fundamental data structure by most of R's modeling software.
A data frame is a list with class “data.frame”. There are restrictions on lists that may be made into data frames, namely :

The components must be vectors (numeric, character, or logical), factors, numeric matrices, lists, or other data frames.

Matrices, lists, and data frames provide as many variables to the new data frame as they have columns, elements, or variables, respectively.

Numeric vectors, logicals and factors are included, and character vectors are coerced to be factors, whose levels are the unique values appearing in the vector.

Vector structures appearing as variables of the data frame must all have the same length, and matrix structures must all have the same row size.

see

   ? data.frame

to learn how to construct a dataframe

   my.data.frame = data.frame(v=1:4,ch=c("a","b","c","d"),n=10)
   my.data.frame
    v ch  n
   1 1  a 10
   2 2  b 10
   3 3  c 10
   4 4  d 10

or

  my.data.frame = data.frame(vector=1:4,character=c("a","b","c","d"),const.vector=10,row.names =c("data1","data2","data3","data4"))
  my.data.frame
        vector character const.vector
  data1      1         a           10
  data2      2         b           10
  data3      3         c           10
  data4      4         d           10

data selection and manipulation

You can extract data from dataframes using the [ [ ] ] and $ sign:

  my.data.frame[["character"]]
  [1] a b c d
  Levels: a b c d
 
  my.data.frame[[2]]
  [1] a b c d
  Levels: a b c d

call the 3rd value of the character vector :

  my.data.frame[[2]][3]
  [1] c
  Levels: a b c d

or using the $ syntax:

my.data.frame$vector
  [1] 1 2 3 4
 
  my.data.frame$character[2:3]
  [1] b c
  Levels: a b c d

You can add single arguments to a data frame, query information, select and manipulate arguments or single values from a dataframe

my.data.frame$new
  NULL
 
  my.data.frame$new = c(10,11,20,40)
  my.data.frame
        vector character const.vector new
  data1      1         a           10  10
  data2      2         b           10  11
  data3      3         c           10  20
  data4      4         d           10  40
  str(my.data.frame)
  'data.frame':	4 obs. of  4 variables:
  $ vector      : int  1 2 3 4
  $ character   : Factor w/ 4 levels "a","b","c","d": 1 2 3 4
  $ const.vector: num  10 10 10 10
  $ new         : num  10 11 20 40

length(object.name) number of elements in an object such as matrix vector or dataframes:

  length(my.data.frame$new) 
  [1] 4

which(object.name) and which.max(object.name) return the index of a specific or of the greatest element of an object

  which.max(my.data.frame$new) 
  [1] 4
 
  which(my.data.frame$new==20) 
  [1] 3

max(object.name) return the value of the greatest element

  max(my.data.frame$new) 
  [1] 40

sort(object.name) sort from small to big

  sort(my.data.frame$new) 
  [1] 10 11 20 40

rev(object.name) from big to small

  rev(sort(my.data.frame$new)) # 
  [1] 40 20 11 10

subset(object.name, …) subset returns a selection of an R-object with respect to criteria ( typically comparisons: x$V1 < 10); if the R-object is a data frame, the option select gives the variables to be kept or dropped using a minus sign

  subset(my.data.frame, my.data.frame$new == 20)
     v ch  n new
   3 3  c 10  20
 
sample(my.data.frame$new, 3)
[1] 10 11 20
 
sample(my.data.frame$new, 3)
[1] 40 10 11
 
sample(my.data.frame$new, 3)
[1] 11 10 40

More examples

The following R commands give an example of the simple procedure of importing data, cleaning a table by extracting relevant information, checking the presence of missing data.

  landuse04=read.csv("~/ost4sem/studycase/Lab_scripts/inputs/2004_landuse.csv", header=TRUE, sep=",", dec=".", na.string=":")
 
  forests04 = subset(landuse04, landuse04$forest.Wooded.area >= 0 )
  forests04$landuse = NULL
  forests04.check=na.fail(forests04)
  forests04$total.Total.area[1] = NA
  forests04.check=na.fail(forests04)
  Error in na.fail.default(forests04) : missing values in object

now recover the situation at the begin with no NA

  forests04 = subset(landuse04, landuse04$forest.Wooded.area >=0 )
  forests04$landuse = NULL
  forests04.check=na.fail(forests04)
  str(forests04)
  'data.frame':   15 obs. of  12 variables:
  data.frame':   15 obs. of  12 variables:
  $ geographic.Unit                     : Factor w/ 72 levels "be10¬†R√©gion de Brxelles-Capitale/Brussels Hoofdstedelijk Gewest",..: 15 2 1 8 3 4 5 6 7 14 ...
  $ total.Total.area                    : num  3052.8 16.1 16.1 1352.2 286.7 ...
  $ agriarea.Utilized.agricultural.area : num  1393.8 0.2 0.2 633.8 91.3 ...
  $ arabland.Arable.land                : num  840 0.2 0.2 430.8 60.2 ...
  $ forest.Wooded.area                  : num  606.5 1.8 1.8 108.1 34 ...
  $ garden.Private.gardens              : num  0.2 0 0 0.1 0 0 0 0 0 0.1 ...
  $ grasland.Permanent.grassland        : num  530 0.1 0.1 181.4 28.7 ...
  $ greenfod.Green.fodder.on.arable.land: num  248.6 0 0 161.4 41.7 ...
  $ fallow.Fallow                       : num  23.6 0 0 7.4 1.1 1.2 1.2 2.3 1.7 16.2 ...
  $ olivepl.Olive.plantations           : int  0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 ...
  $ permcrop.Permanent.crops            : num  21.4 0 0 19.2 1.5 9.7 3.1 4.1 0.9 2.1 ...
  $ vineyard.Vineyards                  : num  0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 ...

Do you see something strange? look at the forests04$geographic.Unit level of factors and the dataframe number of variables !

Let's fix it now!

  library(gdata)
  forests04 = drop.levels(forests04)
  str(forests04)
 
  'data.frame':	15 obs. of  12 variables:
  $ geographic.Unit                     : Factor w/ 15 levels "be1 Région de Bruxelles-Capitale/Brussels Hoofdstedelijk Gewest",..: 15 1 4 2 5 6 7 8 9 3 ...
...

Functions

Functions are themselves objects in R which can be stored in the project's workspace. This provides a simple and convenient way to extend R.
Usage: in writing your own function you provide one or more arguments or names for the function, an expression (or body of the function) and a value is produced equal to the output function result

function(arglist) expr function definition
return(value)

Example

myfunction <- function(x) x^5
myfunction(3)
243
 
body(myfunction) <- quote(5^x)
## or equivalently  body(myfunction) <- expression(5^x)
myfunction(3) 
[1] 125
body(myfunction)
5^x
myfunction
function (x) 
5^x

Species Distribution Modeling II

Script written by Adam M. Wilson, adapted by Marta A. Jarzyna, November 2015

In this session we will: 1. Read in species occurrence and range data 2. Pre-process environmental data 3. Use hSDM package to fit 2 hierarchical Bayesian model while accounting for species imperfect detection 4. Predict across the landscape and compare predictive abilities of both models.

 rm(list=ls(all=TRUE))
 
 #define working directory
 wdir <- "/media/sf_LVM_share" 
 setwd(wdir)
 
 #define data directory - this is where we store the data, but also where we will save the output to
 datadir <- "/media/sf_LVM_share/data" 
 
 # if your shared folder is not writable, create a different folder for the output
 if(!file.exists("~/sdm_out")) dir.create("~/sdm_out", recursive=T)
 outdir <- "~/sdm_out"
 
 # Load necessary libraries
 require(rgdal)
 require(lattice)
 require(ggplot2)
 
 packages=c("hSDM","dismo","maptools","sp",
         "maps","coda","rgdal","rgeos",
         "doParallel","reshape",
         "ggplot2","knitr","rasterVis","texreg")
         
 l=lapply(packages, library, character.only=T,quietly=T)

We will use Montane woodcreper (Lepidocolaptes lacrymiger) as example species. This species has a large range, occurring from the coastal cordillera of Venezuela along the Andes south to south-east Peru and central Bolivia.

 # Read in species occurrence data and species range
 # Species: Montane woodcreper, Lepidocolaptes lacrymiger
 # point occurrence data
 points <- as.data.frame(read.csv("/media/sf_LVM_share/data/occurrence/Lepidocolaptes_lacrymiger_ebird.csv", header=TRUE))
 head(points)
 presence <- matrix(1,nrow(points),1)
 points <- cbind(points,presence)
 
 # retrieving spatial coordinates from a Spatial object
 points <- SpatialPointsDataFrame(points[,c(3,2)], points, coords.nrs = numeric(0), proj4string = CRS(as.character(NA)), match.ID = TRUE)
 projection(points)="+proj=longlat +datum=WGS84 +no_defs +ellps=WGS84 +towgs84=0,0,0"
 plot(points)
 
 # Species' range
 range <- readOGR(".", "cartodb-query")
 range
 plot(range, add=TRUE)
 
 # Check out the data structure:
 head(points[,-1])
 

Explore observer effort: sampling duration, distance travelled, and area surveyed.

 points.m <- as.data.frame(points)
 
 ggplot(points.m,aes(
x=effort_distance_km))+
xlab("Sampling Distance (km)")+
geom_histogram(binwidth = .1)+scale_x_log10()+
geom_vline(xintercept=c(1,5),col="red")

Also note that there are many records with missing spatial certainty values.

 table("Distance/Area"=!is.na(points$effort_distance_km)| !is.na(points$effort_area_ha))

For this exercise, we'll simply remove points with large or unknown spatial uncertainty. Incorporating this spatial uncertainty into distribution models is an active area of research.

 # Filter the data below thresholds specified above using `filter` from the [dplyr library](http://cran.r-project.org/package=dplyr).
 cdis=5     # Distance in km
 points=points[(points$effort_distance_km<=cdis& !is.na(points$effort_distance_km)),]

Load eBird sampling dataset

 # link to global sampling raster
 gsampling=raster(file.path(datadir,"eBirdSampling_filtered.tif"))
 names(gsampling)="trials"
 
 # crop to species range to create modelling domain
 sampling=crop(gsampling,range,file.path(outdir,"sampling.grd"),overwrite=T)   
 # assign projection
 projection(sampling)="+proj=longlat +datum=WGS84 +no_defs +ellps=WGS84 +towgs84=0,0,0"
 
 # convert to points within data region
 # samplingp=as(sampling,"SpatialPointsDataFrame")
 
 # Create a combined presence-nondetection point dataset
 presences=rasterize(as(points,"SpatialPoints"),sampling,fun='count',background=0)
 fitdata=cbind.data.frame(presences=values(presences),trials=values(sampling),coordinates(presences))
 
 ## filter to locations with at least one trial
 fitdata=fitdata[fitdata$trials>0,]
 
 # Convert to a spatialDataFrame to faciliate linking with georeferenced environmental data.
 coordinates(fitdata)=c("x","y")
 projection(fitdata)="+proj=longlat +datum=WGS84 +ellps=WGS84"
 fitdata@data[,c("lon","lat")]=coordinates(fitdata)

Load coastline from maptools package for plotting.

 coast <- map_data("world",
                xlim=c(bbox(range)[1,1]-1,bbox(range)[1,2]+1),
                ylim=c(bbox(range)[2,1]-1,bbox(range)[2,2]+1))

 ggcoast=geom_path(data=coast,aes(x=long,y=lat,group = group),lwd=.1)

Plot Available Species Data

 ggplot(fitdata@data,aes(y=lat,x=lon))+
  ggcoast+ 
  geom_path(data=fortify(range),
          aes(y=lat,x=long,group=piece),
          col="green")+
  geom_point(data=fitdata@data[fitdata$presences==0,],
           aes(x=lon,y=lat),pch=1,
           col="black",cex=.8,lwd=2,alpha=.3)+
  geom_point(data=fitdata@data[fitdata$presences>=1,],
           aes(x=lon,y=lat),pch=3,
           col="red",cex=2,lwd=3,alpha=1)+
  ylab("Latitude")+xlab("Longitude")+
  coord_equal()+
  xlim(c(min(fitdata$lon),max(fitdata$lon)))+
  ylim(c(min(fitdata$lat),max(fitdata$lat)))

Load Environmental Data

 # Like last week, we'll focus on the following variables:
 fenv <- c(
  cld="data/cloud/meanannual.tif",
  cld_intra="data/cloud/intra.tif",
  elev="data/elevation_mn_GMTED2010_mn.tif",
  forest="data/tree_mn_percentage_GFC2013.tif")

To facilitate modelling, let's crop the global rasters to a smaller domain. We can use the extent of the expert range and the crop() function in raster package.

 # crop to species domain and copy to project folder 
 env <- foreach(i=1:length(fenv))%do%{
  fo=file.path(outdir,paste0(names(fenv)[i],"_clipped.grd"))
  crop(raster(file.path(wdir,fenv[i])),range,file=fo,overwrite=T)   
 }

Read the environmental data in as a raster stack

 env <- stack(list.files(path = outdir, pattern="*_clipped.grd$" , full.names = TRUE ))
 env
 #aggregate data to save space
 ag.env <- aggregate(env,4,fun=mean,na.rm=TRUE)
 ag.env
 # rename layers for convenience
 names(ag.env)=names(fenv)
 # mask by elevation to set ocean to 0
 ag.env=mask(ag.env,ag.env[["elev"]],maskvalue=0)
 # check out the plot
 plot(ag.env)

Variable selection is tricky business and we're not going to dwell on it here… We'll use the following variables.

 vars=c("cld","cld_intra","elev","forest")

Scaling and centering the environmental variables to zero mean and variance of 1, using the scale function is typically a good idea. We will do it here so that we can better interpret the regression coefficients.

 senv=scale(ag.env[[vars]])

Covariate correlation

 # Scatterplot matrix of the available environmental data.
 splom(senv,varname.cex=2)

Annotate points with environmental data

 fitdata=raster::extract(senv,fitdata,sp=T)

Due to opportunistic observations of the species, a few grid cells have more observations than trials. Let's remove them:

 table(fitdata$presences>fitdata$trials)
 fitdata=fitdata[fitdata$presences<=fitdata$trials,]
 
 ## omit rows with missing data (primarily ocean pixels)
 fitdata2=na.omit(fitdata@data)
 
 kable(head(fitdata2), format = "markdown")

Then transform the full gridded dataset into a data.frame with associated environmental data for predicting across space.

 pdata=cbind.data.frame(
  coordinates(senv),
  values(senv))
 colnames(pdata)[1:2]=c("lon","lat")
 
 ## omit rows with missing data (primarily ocean pixels)
 pdata=na.omit(pdata)
 
 kable(head(pdata), format = "markdown")

Creating and running the models. This table is similar to the data available from the “Annotate” function in MOL, with the exception that it contains the point data aggregated to the resolution of the environmental data. Let's compare two models, one using interpolated precipitation and the other using satellite-derived cloud data.

 # Set number of chains to fit.
 mods=data.frame(
  model=c("m1","m2"),
  formula=c("~cld+elev",
          "~cld+cld_intra+elev*I(elev^2)+forest"),
  name=c( "Cloud + Elevation",
        "Full Model"))
        
 kable(mods, format = "markdown")

 # Specify model run-lengths. Real model runs generally require far more iterations  to achieve convergence and aquire a suitable sample.  For now, we'll do a very short run:
 burnin=200
 mcmc=100
 thin=1

Fit the models. Both site-occupancy or ZIB models (with hSDM.siteocc() or hSDM.ZIB() functions respectively) can be used to model the presence-absence of a species taking into account imperfect detection. The site-occupancy model can be used in all cases but can be less convenient and slower to fit when the repeated visits at each site are made under the same observation conditions. While this is likely not true in this situation (the observations occurred in different years, etc.), we'll use the simpler model today. For more information about the differences, see the hSDM Vignette Section 4.3.
Example: hSDM.ZIB The model integrates two processes, an ecological process associated to the presence or absence of the species due to habitat suitability and an observation process that takes into account the fact that the probability of detection of the species is less than one. If the species has been observed at least once during multiple visits, we can assert that the habitat at this site is suitable. And the fact that the species can be unobserved at this site is only due to imperfect detection.

In this example we'll assume a spatially constant p(observation|presence), but it's also possible to put in covariates for this parameter.

 # Run the model
 results=foreach(m=1:nrow(mods),.packages="hSDM") %dopar% { 
  ## if foreach/doParallel are not installed, you can use this line instead
  # for(m in 1:nrow(mods)) { 
  tres=hSDM.ZIB(
  suitability=as.character(mods$formula[m]),  #Formula for suitability
  presences=fitdata2$presences,    # Number of Observed Presences
  observability="~1",             # Formula for p(observation|presence)
  trials=fitdata2$trials,          # Number of Trials
  data=fitdata2,             # Covariates for fitting model
  suitability.pred=pdata,        # Covariates for prediction 
  mugamma=0, Vgamma=1.0E6,      # Priors on Gamma
  gamma.start=0,                # Gamma initial Value
  burnin=burnin, mcmc=mcmc, thin=thin,  # MCMC parameters
  beta.start=0,                 # Initial values for betas
  mubeta=0, Vbeta=1.0E6,        # Priors on Beta
  save.p=0,                     # Don't save full posterior on p
  verbose=1,                    # Report progress
  seed=round(runif(1,0,1e6)))   # Random seed
  tres$model=mods$formula[m]      # Add model formula to result
  tres$modelname=mods$name[m]     # Add model name to result
  return(tres)
  }

Summarize and plot posterior parameters

 # The model returns full posterior distributions for all model parameters.  To summarize them you need to choose your summary metric (e.g. mean/median/quantiles). 
 params=foreach(r1=results,.combine=rbind.data.frame,.packages="coda")%do% {
   data.frame(model=r1$model,
           modelname=r1$modelname,
           parameter=colnames(r1$mcmc),
           mean=summary(r1$mcmc)$statistics[,"Mean"],
           sd=summary(r1$mcmc)$statistics[,"SD"],
           median=summary(r1$mcmc)$quantiles[,"50%"],
           HPDinterval(mcmc(as.matrix(r1$mcmc))),
           RejectionRate=rejectionRate(r1$mcmc))}

 # plot it
 ggplot(params[!grepl("Deviance*",rownames(params)),],
     aes(x=mean,y=parameter,colour=modelname))+
  geom_errorbarh(aes(xmin=lower,xmax=upper,height=.1),lwd=1.5)+
  geom_point(size = 3)+xlab("Standardized Coefficient")+
  ylab("Parameter")+
  theme(legend.position="bottom")

Detection probability

 # The model uses repeat observations within cells to estimate the probability observation given that the species was present.  
 pDetect <-   params[params$parameter=="gamma.(Intercept)",c("modelname","mean")]
 pDetect$delta.est <- inv.logit(pDetect$mean)
 colnames(pDetect)[2]="gamma.hat"
 kable(pDetect,row.names=F, format = "markdown")

How does this change if you add environmental covariates to the observability regression?

 # Predictions for each cell
 pred=foreach(r1=results,.combine=stack,.packages="raster")%dopar% {
 tr=rasterFromXYZ(cbind(x=pdata$lon,
                       y=pdata$lat,
                       pred=r1$prob.p.pred))
  names(tr)=r1$modelname    
  return(tr)
  }

Compare the model predictions

 predscale=scale_fill_gradientn(values=c(0,.5,1), colours=c('white','darkgreen','green'), na.value="transparent")

 # set plotting limits using expert range above
 gx=xlim(extent(env)@xmin,extent(env)@xmax)
 gy=ylim(extent(env)@ymin,extent(env)@ymax)
 
 gplot(pred,maxpixels=1e5)+geom_raster(aes(fill=value)) +
  facet_wrap(~ variable) +
  predscale+
  coord_equal()+
  geom_path(data=fortify(range),
          aes(y=lat,x=long,group=piece),
          fill="red",col="red")+
  geom_point(data=fitdata@data[fitdata$presences==0,],
           aes(x=lon,y=lat,fill=1),pch=1,col="black",cex=.8,lwd=2,alpha=.3)+
  geom_point(data=fitdata@data[fitdata$presences>=1,],
           aes(x=lon,y=lat,fill=1),pch=3,col="red",cex=2,lwd=3,alpha=1)+
  ggcoast+gx+gy+ylab("Latitude")+xlab("Longitude")+
  labs(col = "p(presence)")+
  coord_equal()

Additional Models are available in the hSDM

The *.icar functions in hSDM add spatial effects to the model as well, accounting for spatial autocorrelation of species occurrence.
hSDM.binomial & hSDM.binomial.iCAR Simple and spatial binomial model (perfect detection).

hSDM.ZIB & hSDM.ZIB.iCAR & hSDM.ZIB.iCAR.alteration Zero-inflated Binomial (example we used today).

hSDM.ZIP & hSDM.ZIP.iCAR & hSDM.ZIP.iCAR.alteration Zero-inflated Poisson (Abundance data with imperfect detection).

hSDM.siteocc & hSDM.siteocc.iCAR Incorporates temporally varying environment to account for changing observation conditions.

hSDM.poisson & hSDM.poisson.iCAR Simple and spatial poisson model for species abundance (perfect detection).

hSDM.Nmixture & hSDM.Nmixture.iCAR Poisson model for abundance with imperfect detection.

Registration Fees

THE REGISTRATION PROCESS IS CLOSED

The training was sold out few days after the open call. If you like, send us an email and we can add you to our waiting list. You will be contacted if a place will become available or if we organize a new training.

Registration is on a first come, first served basis and it will be closed when it reaches 25 participants. Therefore, we encourage participant to register ASAP. A waiting list will be establish in case of over-passing the 25 participants.

The course Registration Fee Includes: 42 hours class training, student supervision, course auditing, course material, lectures, sample data and a USB flash drive inclusive of Linux Virtual Machine with all the software installed, six lunch bag (with local product), and a social dinner (Friday night). ECTA credits and/ or attendance certificate can be requested.

We establish different registration fees in accordance to the per capita gross domestic product of the European Union member states and the nearby countries. This allows to have a more fair registration fee for poorer countries, facilitating their residents to attend the course without too much difficulties.

In order to register, all participants have to:

1) Pay the registration fee in accordance with the location of their institution (see the table below).
You will be considered registered ONCE the registration fee has been paid through the bank transfer to the following bank account and the questionnaire has been filled in (see below)

No-Euro Zone Paypal is also possible. Please mail to me.

By the way, before to make the bank transfer keep in touch with giuseppe.amatulli@gmail.com to be sure that the course is not already sold out.

2) fill-in the following questionnaire and send an e-mail to giuseppe.amatulli@gmail.com with your name, affiliation, questionnaire-name, and the bank transfer confirmation.

Overview of Conference fee.

Fees | Institution/State (based on per capita gross domestic product ranking list)
350 Euro | EU institution & International Organizations - Luxembourg - Norway - Switzerland - Denmark - Ireland - Austria - The Netherlands - Belgium - France - Sweden - Finland - Germany - Iceland - United Kingdom - Malta - other countries
300 Euro | Italy* - Spain - Greece - Cyprus - Czech Republic - Slovakia - Estonia - Slovenia - Lithuania - Poland - Hungary - Portugal - Latvia
250 Euro | University of Basilicata* - Croatia - Bulgaria - Turkey - Romania - Belarus - Serbia - Albania - Bosnia - Republic of Macedonia - Ukraine - Moldova - Kosovo - Montenegro - other developing countries

* Students from Italian institutions (not considering UNIBAS students) benefit of 4 places reserved.
* Students from the University of Basilicata benefit of lowest fees rate and 6 places reserved as compensation for hosting the event.

Refund policy

Written notification of registration cancellation must be e-mailed to giuseppe.amatulli@gmail.com. If registration cancellation is received by April 1, 2015, registrant will receive a refund of registration fee less a $100 processing fee. We will retain 250€ for cancellation notice submitted after April 1, 2015 unless candidates from waiting list accept to replace withdrawal candidates.

Registration List & Registration Waiting List